<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon prepared to be preached at the funerall of Walter Norbane, esq;  by W. Haywood Dr. in divinity: one of the chaplains in ordinary to his late Majesty of glorious memory.</title>
            <author>Haywood, William, 1599 or 1600-1663.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1663</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 72 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86131</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1239</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1027_16</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208879</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867796</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867796</idno>
            <idno type="VID">168881</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86131)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 168881)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 152:E1027[16])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon prepared to be preached at the funerall of Walter Norbane, esq;  by W. Haywood Dr. in divinity: one of the chaplains in ordinary to his late Majesty of glorious memory.</title>
                  <author>Haywood, William, 1599 or 1600-1663.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 31, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Richard Thrale at the Cross-Keyes at S. Pauls-Gate, entring into Cheapside,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June 16".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Funeral sermons --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:168881:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREPARED To be preached at the FUNERALL of <hi>WALTER NORBANE,</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
            </head>
            <p>BY W. HAYWOOD Dr. in DIVINITY: One of the Chaplains in ordinary to his late MAJESTY of Glorious Memory.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed for <hi>Richard Thrale</hi> at the <hi>Croſs-Keyes</hi> at S. <hi>Pauls</hi>-Gate, entring into <hi>Cheapſide.</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:168881:2"/>
            <head>To the truly Virtuous and Worthy Miſtreſs <hi>Mary Norbane,</hi> Relict of <hi>Walter Norbane,</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> deceaſed.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat I had no deſire or meaning thus to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in print, when I firſt undertook this Funeral Sermon, I ſuppoſe on my ſingle aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeveration will eaſily be believed: But that the Sermon ſhould be at the very instant of the delivery, in ſo honourable, ſo full an Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience defeated and ſilenced, is a thing not ſo eaſie to be believed, without the atteſtation of many Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; That one ſingle perſon uſurping the Office of a Miniſter, but neither a Graduate, nor in Orders, nor ſcant of Age to be, nor ever intending (as I am informed) any way, old or new, to be, ſhould by his clamorous impudence and ſhameleſs railing confound ſuch a Solemnity, ſilence the Preacher ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing in the Pulpit, and drive all, that met to do honour to the memory of ſo worthy a Gentleman, out of the Church with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Sermon, is an example of <hi>pity</hi> and boy-like petulance, ſuch as I think can hardly be paralelled. Eſpecially, ſith neither the deceaſed Gentleman (for ought I know) nor the Preacher had ever affronted or provoked the ſaid inſolent Party in word or deed. My own wrong (I thank God) I leaſt value, having learned by experience to bear many cauſeleſs
<pb facs="tcp:168881:3"/>injuries with patience. But the wrong done to the deceaſed (a ſingular Ornament to this Countrey and to his Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) together with the injury and contempt of ſo noble an Auditory, conſiſting of Lords, Knights, Parliament-men, Eſquires, Gentlemen, Officers of the County and Reverend Divines, ſo many, as in divers years hath not been ſeen in <hi>Caln</hi>-Church the like Congregation; ſuch an inſolence may not ſo well be paſſed over in ſilence, nor ſo Worthy a Company utterly defrauded of what they came to hear. I have therefore yielded to the requeſt of divers friends that the Sermon may be publiſhed, and not buried with him, whoſe Memory and Vertues deſerves never to be buried. And I have thought fit to dedicate it to you, by whoſe requeſt it was undertaken, and who can beſt witneſſe how little I ſued or ſought for the employment. Beſeeching God it may help to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigate your ſorrow for ſo invaluable a loſſe, and add ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what to your comfort, and remain as a Monument of his good will to you and yours: who is many wayes obliged to be, and to continue</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your truly loving Friend and Neighbour WILLIAM HAYVVOOD.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:168881:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON At the Funeral of <hi>Walter Norbane</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> 
               <hi>April.</hi> 13 1659. at <hi>Calne</hi> Church in <hi>Wiltſhire,</hi> prepared to be preached.</head>
            <q>
               <bibl>ROM. 6.5.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>For if we have been planted together into the likeneſs of his Death, we ſhall be alſo into the likeneſs of his Reſurrection.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F Chriſts Death and Reſurrection it is, that the Apoſtle here ſpeaks, exhorting us to be planted into the one, that we may at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to the likeneſs of the other.</p>
            <p>The time of the year borders upon the annual Memory of our Saviours Death and Reſurrection; and it is a ſeaſon alſo of planting and growing up: but God hath made it, to our great ſorrow, a time of felling and hewing down. We have beheld the fall of this worthy Gentleman, whoſe remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:168881:4"/>lie here before us, as the fall of ſome great Tree, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der whoſe ſhadow many leſſer plants were ſhelter'd. A Tree of no little ornament, benefit, relief and comfort to the poor Inhabitants of this place wherein he lived. And much to our ſorrow it adds, that there appears not ſo near again any of like dignity, age, and fair abilities to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare with him.</p>
            <p>Howbeit, if we could be perſwaded, this cutting down were but a new Plantation, and a plantation of great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to him, how much loſs ſoever to us, that might avail ſomewhat to mitigate our ſorrow; And that (I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe) this Text may help to perſwade us, for there we hear of a plantation into Chriſts Death, ſo that Death it ſelf to them that are in Chriſt, is but a kind of plantation, and their burial, a kind of ſowing: So our Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.42. <hi>It is ſown in corruption, it is raiſed in incorruption: It is ſown in diſhonour, it is raiſed in glory: it is ſown in weakneſſe, it is raiſed in power.</hi> So our bleſſed Saviour, <hi>Except a Corn of wheat fall into the ground, and die, it abideth alone, but if it die, it bringeth forth much fruit,</hi> John 12.24. Chriſt himſelf therefore choſe to die, and his Burial to him proved but a planting; His Body in three dayes roſe again, with an encreaſe of Immortality; and Chriſt neither died nor roſe for himſelf, but is become the firſt fruits of them that ſleep, and the pattern of them that ſhall riſe again: For, as is the Heavenly <hi>Adam,</hi> ſo they alſo that are heavenly, And as we have born the Image of the earthy, we ſhall alſo bear the Image of the Heavenly; But there muſt be a change firſt, for fleſh and blood cannot inherit the Kingdom of God, neither may corruption inherit incorrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion There muſt be a plantation therefore, firſt into the death of Chriſt, a fellowſhip with his ſufferings, (as St. <hi>Paul</hi> calls it) a conformity to his Paſſion, which if we patiently undergo, the Text then hath a comfortable promiſe, that will not fail us: <hi>For if we have been planted into the likeneſs of his Death, we ſhall be alſo into the likeneſs of his Reſurrection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it will be ſaid, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks not here of our planting into Chriſt, by a natural death, but rather by a
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:168881:4"/>moral, or a myſtical: for immediately before, he inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth in Baptiſm: <hi>Buryed</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>by Baptiſm into death;</hi> That like as Chriſt was raiſed by the glory of the Father, ſo we ſhould walk in newneſs of life. And at the eleventh ver. <hi>Likewiſe reckon ye your ſelves alſo, to be dead unto ſin, but alive unto God, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi> So that the planting into our Saviours Death, which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> here intends, is by a death unto ſin, not by a death in the grave.</p>
            <p>And this we deny not; And even in this reſpect, we have not only a comfortable Scripture over the dead, but full of good inſtruction alſo, and edification to the living; So would Funeral Sermons be. They are for the behoof of the living, rather than the dead; That as the Apoſtle ſaith of Propheſie, <hi>He that propheſieth ſpeaks unto men, to edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, and exhortation, and comfort;</hi> ſo by ſuch preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Chriſtians might not only be comforted, but edified likewiſe, and exhorted. Now for edification, a Scripture more effectual can hardly be found, than this; For it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends the ſumme of all vertuous and godly living; To be planted into Chriſts Death, that thereby we may grow to his Reſurrection; that is, To die to ſin, and live to Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs; Ceaſe to do evil, and learn to do well: Put off the old Man, that we may be planted into the New: And, what is there more in Chriſtianity to be done?</p>
            <p>Yet though this be the neareſt, and moſt genuine Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of the Apoſtle, ſo to underſtand him, as ſpeaking of mortification, and riſing to a new life; the other way of applying this Text to men naturally dying, or preſſed with great tribulations, may not be excluded as altogether im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper. For even to that purpoſe alſo Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in other places applyeth this very Metaphor, of dying and riſing with Chriſt: as 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.8. <hi>We are troubled on every ſide, but not diſtreſſed: Perſecuted, but not forſaken: alwayes bearing about in our body the dying of the Lord Jeſus, that the life alſo of Jeſus might be manifeſt,</hi> &amp;c. And though re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling Chriſts Death, and Riſing by true Repentance, and a holy Life, be the moſt excellent, and moſt profitable way
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:168881:5"/>of imitating him; as without which outward ſuffering, availe little, and therefore that ſenſe needs moſt exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Yet we cannot deny ſuch a conformity to Chriſts Death by our ſufferings, to be a neerer way and more fully reſembling the likeneſſe of his plantation. As our riſing from corruption to glory draweth neerer the like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Chriſts Reſurrection, than our riſing to newneſſe of life onely: So our planting into Chriſts Death, by a fellowſhip of his ſufferings, and by being brought down to the grave with him, is a neerer and fuller reſemblance of his paſſion, than the Death of true repentance and mortification to ſin only, if no other affliction be added.</p>
            <p>But how much more full, if both be joyned together? As in this our deceaſed brother to my knowledge they were, an afflicted Body, and a penitent ſoule, a ſelf-deniyn life, and a patient and lamb like death, a fleſh crucified with the affections and luſt, and a ſpirit raiſed and revived with hope of immortality, a ſoule aſpiring to heaven, while his body ſunk to the earth. What nearer, what fuller, what truer or more immediate planting into the death and Reſurrection of Chriſt? And he that is ſo farre in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporated, what Text can fit him better. <hi>For if we have thus been planted into the likeneſſe of our Saviours Death, We ſhall be alſo, into the likeneſſe of his Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We proced to a diviſion of our Text. Two plantations in this Scripture appeare joyned in connexion, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred one upon the other: The one a ſad and heavy plantation, the other a joyfull and comforting, the one in weeping and mourning, the other in triumph and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rejoycing, the one may be called our Winner plantation, the other our Summer; If not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the one our ſeed time, the other our harveſt, out Winter planation or ſeed-time. <hi>For if ye have been planted together, into the likeneſſe of Chirſts Death.</hi> And our Summer plantation, or harveſt, <hi>Ye ſhall be alſo
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:168881:5"/>into the likeneſſe of his Reſurrection.</hi> The former of theſe containes our conflict, the later our Crown: Not more bitterneſſe and pains in the one, than comfort and ſweetneſſe in the other.</p>
            <p>We begin with the former, which is our Winter plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, or ſowing in tears. <hi>For if we have been planted into the likeneſſe of Chriſt's Death.</hi> Where the firſt word that meets us is the Conjunction <hi>Si,</hi> implying a Condition, <hi>Si complantati fuerimus,</hi> If we have been planted. Giving us to know, that theſe two plantations are ſo connected one to the other, as our labour and our reward, our warfare and our victory; that without having our part in the former, there is no hope of attaining the latter; unleſſe we firſt communicate in the Winter plantation of our Lords Death; at the ſummer plantation of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection there will be no arriving. Except we firſt ſuffer with him, no hope of reigning. It is the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles way of arguing, for ſome length together, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he perſwades <hi>Timothy</hi> to endure hardneſſe, as a good ſouldier of Jeſus Chriſt, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.3. If a man ſtrive for Maſteries, yet he is not crowned, except he ſtrive law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully. The husbandman that laboureth, muſt be firſt par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of the fruits. Remember that Chriſt firſt died, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he roſe againe, and it is a faithfull ſaying, If we be dead with him, we believe, we ſhall alſo live with him.</p>
            <p>So the two plantations are inſeparable; and rightly we may conclude; if any man miſſe his part in the later, it is for lack of the former; if any attaine not to the Reſurrection of Chriſt, it is becauſe he failed in the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, which may be the reaſon perhaps, why the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle thus puts it upon an <hi>If,</hi> as a thing to be doubted of: <hi>If we have been planted into his Death.</hi> For ſo hard appeares the condition, and ſo rate the number of them that are truely ſo planted, that it may well be doubted, and doubted of the beſt of us all.</p>
            <p>Inſomuch that the Apoſtle ſpeaks here in the firſt perſon, as if he doubted of himſelf for company. If
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:168881:6"/>we have been planted, fully and throughly, into the like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Chriſts Death. And it is but what ye find in the third to the <hi>Phillipians, All things. I account but dung, that I may be found in him, with the fellowſhip of his ſufferings, being made conformable to his death: If by any meanes, I might attaine to the Reſurrection of the dead; Not as if I had allready attained, or were allready perfect: But I follow after, if I may apprehend,</hi> Phillip. 3, 12. <hi>If I may apprehend;</hi> So that he doubts of his own ſufferings likewiſe, and whether this firſt plantation be compleat with himſelf.</p>
            <p>Ye ſee therefore that he uſeth the preterperfectenſe alſo. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. If we have been planted. Have been, that we deſire to be, that we intend to be: every one will be ready to ſay, and no <hi>If,</hi> no doubt upon that. All the feare is, whether or no we have allready enough of this plantation. Which makes him ſay in another place, <hi>I fill up, that which is behind, of the afflictions of Christ in my fleſh, Coloſſ.</hi> 1.24. <hi>As</hi> if ſomewhat in this kind, were ſtill wanting on his part; and therefore well may he utter it with <hi>Si, &amp; ſi Dubitantis; If we have been allready planted ſufficiently, into the likeneſſe, of his Death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doubted it may be the rather, becauſe of the prepoſition <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> here added; <hi>Si complantati</hi> faith the latine, if we have been planted together, which is diverſly expounded, together with Chriſt, or together with one another. Together with Chriſt, If we have been obedient as he was, to the Death, not ſhrinking from our pattern, ſo much as in a wiſh but reſolved with him, who when he ſaw the cup coming, prayed, not my will O Father, but thine be done. And then, together with out brethren, If we have not deſerted out companions in ſuffering, <hi>As</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> complaines of <hi>Demas,</hi> that he <hi>had forſaken him, and embraced this preſent world, 3 Tim.</hi> 4.10. And, at my firſt anſwer (to wit before <hi>Nero</hi>) No man ſtood with me, but all forſook me, <hi>Si complantati</hi> may teach us, that ſuffering together in a good cauſe, is
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:168881:6"/>as acceptable as praying together. They do not well there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, who withdraw from times of Common humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſuch as the Memorial of our Lords Paſſion, and his faſting in the Wilderneſſe; times ordained to make this <hi>Complantati</hi> as univerſal and as full as may be, that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians may be planted together into the ſimilitude of their Saviours Death.</p>
            <p>Two obſervations more by the way here offer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: One upon <hi>Plantati,</hi> another upon <hi>Mortem.</hi> Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Plantati,</hi> that it is not any ſlight Conformity, or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity with the Death of Chriſt will ſerve turn. Though it be but <hi>in ſimilitudinem,</hi> yet it is more than <hi>aſſimilati.</hi> It is not if we reſemble it, if we imitate or draw near it; But <hi>Si complantati,</hi> if we have been planted into it, which argueth a nearer Conjunction, more firm and inſeparable: For that which is planted, or grafted (ſo the word ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth) groweth into one nature with that, whereto it is joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. It partakes of one life, one ſpirit with the Root, and never decayes ſo long as it hath Communion therewith. We are not waxed or ſoder'd, or pinn'd to the Body of Chriſt, to be ſhaken off with foul weather, melted with the flames of perſecution, or unty'd by Satans cunning: but we are planted, there to abide, there to grow, and thrive, and encreaſe.</p>
            <p>To thrive and encreaſe: for planting inferrs fruitful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: Chriſts death is no barren ſoyl, his Body no un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitfull Tree: It yielded an encreaſe with him to life ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting, and muſt yield an encreaſe with us. An encreaſe, and no ſmall one. For Chriſts Body is a Vine, of all plants the moſt fruitfull; I am the Vine, ye are the bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and my Father the Husbandman, <hi>Every branch that beareth fruit, he purgeth it, that it may bring forth more fruit: If it bear none, be takes it away,</hi> &amp;c. John 15.6.</p>
            <p>Nor will it ſuffice, that for a while we bring forth fruit, unleſſe we continue ſo. Branches that are grafted, Slips that are planted, if they live, are never at a ſtay, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes encreaſing, to imitate our daily and inceſſant growth in Grace; Therefore is the Goſpel of the Kingdom likened
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:168881:7"/>to a grain of Muſtard ſeed, to Leaven ſpreading through a whole Lump; the Corn riſing and growing: firſt the blade, then the ear, and then the full Corn in the ear, and never at a ſtand till it be quite ripe. If young Imps newly grafted, do not thrive and encreaſe, it is a ſigne they are not well joyned: they have not communion with the Root.</p>
            <p>Communion with the Root may be another reaſon, why the Apoſtle chooſeth this Metaphor of Planting. The fruit, be it more or leſs, receives all its vigour from the Root; while it derives from thence, it flouriſheth and multiply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth; when it ceaſeth to draw from thence, it withers; to intimate therefore the power of all well-doing, of all the fruit we bear, is derived from the Merits of Chriſt and his Paſſion, not from any natural vigour of ours; therefore we hear of planting into his Death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Into his Death,</hi> leads us to another obſervation concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Mortem.</hi> That into any other reſemblance of Chriſt, it will not ſuffice us to have been planted: if we ſhrink from this, it will not ſerve turn that we have been planted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his life, or his leſſer ſufferings: As his cauſeleſs envy, his undeſerved infamy, perſecution, ſtripes and wounds, if we reach not to a Communion with his Death. Firſt, by Mortification, that the fleſh be curcified, with the affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and luſts, and we can ſay, no longer I, but Chriſt lives in me; and the life that I now live, is no more to my ſelf, but to him that dyed for me, and roſe again. And then by conſtancy in Obedience, that we be faithfull to the death; that neither famine, nor nakedneſſe, peril or ſword, be able to ſeparate us from his love. This is <hi>in ſamilitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem mort is,</hi> into the likeneſſe of his Death: without which, all communion with his life will do no good.</p>
            <p>Farther yet: It may be doubted, why Saint <hi>Paul</hi> adds <hi>In Similitudinem,</hi> not into Chriſts Death, but into the like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his Death. It is (as ſome think) to comfort thoſe, who by a mortified life, ſtriving after their Pattern, reach it but imperfectly. That though they attain not a full Communion or Identity with their Copy; they may not be diſheartened, while they reach a ſimilitude. For a ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:168881:7"/>may be enough for us. Chriſt dyed bodily: It may ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, that we die ſpiritually. Chriſt died to make ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: We to make good our belief of his ſatisfaction: Chriſt died for ſin: we not for, but to ſin. Chriſt for the ſinnes of the whole world: we for no ſinnes, but our own. Nor for our own neither, by way of expiation; for we cannot ſatisfie Juſtice, but by way of ceſſation, that we commit them no more: Chriſt was crucified on the Croſs literally, God ſend our affections and luſts to be crucified myſtically. So perfectly mortified was he, as to know no ſin; we, if we can get ſo far as not to ſerve ſin, it will be well. In Chriſt both nature and mortality was deſtroyed, but not ſin; for he knew no ſin: In us, not Nature, nor Mortality, till the time of our diſſolution, but ſin only: Chriſts death and riſing again was by his own power; <hi>I have power to lay down my life, and power to take it up again,</hi> John 10.18. ſo cannot ours be. Our ſpiritual dying and riſing, is all by his ayd and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sſtance, and vertue of our planting into him, and without him we can do nothing; ſo ye ſee a wide diſparity 'twixt his manner of dying and ours. And therefore well may it be <hi>in ſimilitudinem:</hi> not planted into his death, but into the likeneſs of his death.</p>
            <p>But in what points then holds the ſimilitudes of being planted into that likeneſs (ye will ask) ſith in theſe it holds not? Nay, firſt enquire what be the right wayes of thus plant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, for there appear more than one. As there are two ſorts of Croſſes belonging to a Chriſtian, one of Mortification, another of Martyrdome or Tribulation: ſo two kinds of planting into Chriſts death; The one voluntary, by beating down our bodies, by crucifying the fleſh with the affections and luſts: and the other involuntary, by perſecutions, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtations, and troubles for a good conſcience: which all that will live godly in Chriſt Jeſus, muſt expect their ſhare of.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> calls theſe two ſeveral kinds of Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: the one belonging to times of Warre, the other to times of Peace. In times of Warre (ſaith he) <hi>Ponenda eſt anima,</hi> we muſt jeopard our lives for a good conſcience, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:168881:8"/>imitate Chriſts Death that way. In times of Peace, <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genda carnis deſideria,</hi> the wanton deſires of the fleſh to be broken and crucified. The one of theſe ye have in St. <hi>Pauls Caſtigo corpus: I beat down my body, and bring it into ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection,</hi> 1 Cor. 9.27. There's the Croſſe of mortification: and the other in <hi>facti ſumus ſpectaculum,</hi> we are made a Spectacle to the World, to Angels, and to Men: <hi>We hunger and thirty, and are buffered. Being reviled we bleſs, being perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted we bear it: being defamed we entreat; we are made as the filth of the world, and are as the off-ſcowing of all things to this day,</hi> 1 Cor. 4.13. There's the Croſſe of Tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Of theſe two Martyrdomes: the firſt is more excellent, becauſe it belongeth to all Chriſtians, and is at all times to be practiſed. Nor is the Croſſe of Tribulation acceptable at all, unleſs the Croſſe of mortification be joyned with it: but add both together, and then ye have the neareſt conformity to the Croſſe of Chriſt that can be. When a heart cleanſed from ſinfull corruptions, and perfumed with ſanctifying Graces, is beaten in the Morter of Tribulation, is threſhed with the ſtaile of perſecution and ſends forth the ſweet odour of Praiſe and Thankſgiving; rejoycing under the Croſſe, it is one of the moſt pleaſing ſacrifices to God, and the neareſt reſembling Chriſts', that may be imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
            <p>To touch upon both theſe in a few words: That the Croſſe of Mortification, may moſt nearly be brought to the ſimilitude of Chriſts Death; obſerve from the words of our Text, <hi>ſimilitudinem mortis,</hi> That it be not a defective or half mortifying in ſome parts, not in all, having our tongues bridled it may be, and our hearts looſe: out looks and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures ſanctified, but our actions in ſecret, lawleſs: our volup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous deſires curbed, but covetous ones untied. Our intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance pruned and pared, but our revenge and malice over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grown. This is not <hi>in ſimilitudinem mortis:</hi> for Death ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters all limbs, deprives all ſences, extinguiſhes all faculties: And Chriſt when he was crucified, had every member ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on the Croſs, not any eſcaped the paines of it: if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:168881:8"/>mortifie ſome vices and ſpare others, as <hi>Saul</hi> deſtroyed <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lek</hi> in part, and ſpared <hi>Agag;</hi> if we leave a beloved ſin uncru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, this is not the likeneſſe of Death, but of mutilation on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; it is not <hi>in mortem,</hi> while we ſuffer the ſmalleſt known ſin to eſcape vengeance.</p>
            <p>Not maimed then let our mortifying be; Nor ſecondly inconſtant, that we return again to the works of ſin; for dead men return no more to life. And thirdly, let there be no more motion, nor remembrance of former follies: Let not our hearts fall a longing as the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when they remembred the Onions and Fleſhpots, and Fiſh and Melons of <hi>Aegypt:</hi> for they that are dead, are dead to all love and liking, and have no more remembrance of the things of this life. Fourthly, Let not the pains of morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying deter us neither; for if it be in the likeneſs of Chriſts Death, he dyed (we know) a painful Death. Think not the crucifying of our naughty luſts, will prove an eaſie dying, but then believe it true and unfeigned, when it puts us to trouble and grief.</p>
            <p>Theſe four then, may help to try our mortifying, whether our plantation come home to the pattern of Chriſts Death, or no: that is to ſay, if it be an entire mortifying, and in all parts diffuſed: for it is Death, not a maiming. If it put us to ſore pangs and ſtruglings, for it is a painfull Death, and a Crucifying. If it utterly aboliſh all delightfull remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brances, all longings and deſires toward ſin; for it is Death, not a ſickning or ſwowning. And fourthly, If it be a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant mortifying, that we return no more to the works of ſin: for it is Death, and not a ſleeping. The firſt of theſe diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Hypocrites, which mortifie by halves. The ſecond ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and delicate ones, that will not abide the paines of a thorow mortifying. The third, waverers and languiſhers, whoſe hearts hang after the pleaſures of ſin. The fourth, babkſliders and revolters, that return with the dog to the vomit, and the ſow to the mire again. If our mortifying fail in none of theſe four particulars, it is a good ſign it comes home; and the firſt way of planting into Chriſts Death is ſound and uncounterfeit.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:168881:9"/>
            <p>But then neither may the ſecond way be omitted, after the Croſſe of mortification, muſt be expected the Croſſe of tribulation, to trie whether our plantation be firm and right; when the Potters veſſel is well faſhio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, it muſt be brought to the fire, that it may be hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. And <hi>the fire ſhall trie evry mans work of what ſort it is,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.13. No ſooner was <hi>Job</hi> perceived to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and upright, but Satan deſired to trie him, and the like with the Apoſtle, whom he would fain have ſifted as wheat: the higheſt of all the eight <hi>Beatitudes,</hi> is, Bleſſed they that ſuffer perſecution, for righteouſneſſe ſake; If perſecution ſhake us, it is a ſigne we are firmly planted then indeed. And it is Gods mercy to his own, to ſend them a right experience of themſelves in perſecution, that they may be aſſured their mortification is unfained; tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation worketh experience, and experience hope, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth not aſhamed, And if any be made aſhamed, that is, fall away through ſtormes of perſecution, he may impute it to the lack of ſound mortification, his firſt planting was not firme.</p>
            <p>Well, but how may our planting either way be examined, whether it be ſound and firme, according to Chriſts like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe or no? How, but by the vertues which were moſt eminent and conſpicuous in the Croſſe of Chriſt, and made his ſufferings ſo acceptable. Now they are chiefly foure, which <hi>Bernard</hi> likens to the foure quarters of the Croſſe, each of them ſerving to make up the compleat body of a Chriſtian ſuffering; that is to ſay, Humility, and Charity, and Patience and Conſtancy.</p>
            <p>Humility firſt: for Chriſt humbled himſelf, and became obedient to Death, even the Death of the Croſſe: And if he ſo humbled that had no ſin, how much rather we, that are ſo full of ſin? humillity teaching us to think the worſt of our ſelves, will perſwade us all the ſufferings that fall upon us, are leſſe than we have deſerved. <hi>He hath not dealt with us according to our ſins, nor rewarded us after our iniquities.</hi> And conſequently, teach us with meekneſſe to ſubmit to the ſcourge: Righteous art thou (O lord) in
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:168881:9"/>all thou haſt brought upon us: The end of the Croſſe is indeed to humble us: If any repine at it, and grow not more lowly by it, he makes not the right uſe of it.</p>
            <p>Secondly Charity or Obedience, which proves our lowlineſle, for in the Death of Chriſt was manifeſted the height hof Charity. <hi>Greater love hath no man than this, that he lay down his life for his friend.</hi> How great was his then, that layd down his life for his enemies? And Love is the fulfilling of the law: Charity is the ſumme of obedience. It ſuffereth long, and is kind, and thinks no evil, heark how it ſpeaks from the croſſe: <hi>Father forgive them, for they know not what they do!</hi> And, Lord, <hi>lay not this ſin to their charge,</hi> ſaith the firſt Martyr, with his laſt breath. If we be ſo charitable in our ſufferings, as to returne bleſſing for curſing, prayers for perſecutions, it is a ſigne our plantation into the death of Chriſt is ſtrong and mighty indeed: as the contrary diſcovers a weake Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>For Thirdly, if our conformity be right, it muſt add Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, a vertue in Chriſts ſuffering moſt eminent. Who <hi>As a ſheep led to the ſlaughter, and as a lamb before the ſhearers is dumb; ſo he opened not his mouth:</hi> He ſhall not crie, nor ſtrive, neither ſhall any man heare his voyce in the ſtreets. I became dumb, and opened not my mouth (faith <hi>David</hi>) for it was thy doing; this ſilent ſubmitting, this patient bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, this ſtill lying, and making no noyſe, is that which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth us true Gold indeed, for that melts in ſilence and makes no noyſe: as wheat alſo abides quiet under the flayle, while Chaffe flieth in the face of them that ſmite it.</p>
            <p>Fourthly Conſtancy, the Crowne of all the reſt, for only <hi>He that indureth to the end ſhall be ſaved.</hi> Moſt eminent, this was in our Saviours Croſſe; when all the bitter ſcoffes of his enemies, could not move him to come down. <hi>Let Chriſt the King of Iſrael come down from the Croſſe, and we will believe him?</hi> No, they are not to be believed that ſay it, Chriſt having loved his own, continued to love them to the end, and would not leave the work of our Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:168881:10"/>unperfect, and loſe the fruit of all for lack of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie: let patience (ſaith St. <hi>James</hi>) have her perfect work, And the perfection of Patince is Conſtancy, that we be not weary of well doing; nor tired out with innocent ſuffering: But wait on the Lord, till he deliver us, committing the keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our ſoules to him in well doing, as to a faithfull Creator. <hi>I know whom I have beleeved, and he is able to keep, what is committed to him.</hi> 2 Tim. 1.12</p>
            <p>Add theſe foure vertues together, and then your ſufferings may appeare ſomewhat like your Saviours: Let them be hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, without confidence in your ſelves: Charitable, having compaſſion and praying for others: patient and ſilent, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out complaint or murmurring: Conſtant, and continued to the end, without wavering or revolting; And then your plantation is proved to be ſound and firme, ye are thus without doubt, <hi>Planted into the ſimilitude of Chriſts Death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Eſpecially, if you be faithfull to the Death, for that makes all ſure. <hi>Be faithfull to the Death, and I will give thee a Crown of life.</hi> Death ends the conflict, puts all out of hazard, gets the Conqueſt, and crowns the conqueror, for it foils the laſt, and worſt of all our enemies, even Satan and all his forces. As by the Croſſe of mortification we die to the fleſh; and by the Croſſe of Tribulation, we die to the world: ſo by the Croſſe of a naturall Death, we die to all the temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Satan; And are then paſt our winter plantation without doubt, and ſtand ready for our ſummer, that followeth in the Text, as the ſecond General of our diviſion, and the Reward annexed to the painefull coudition. <hi>For if we have been plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into the likeneſſe of his Death, we ſhall be alſo into the likeneſſe of his Reſurrection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A promiſe (I told you) this part is: and ſuch a one, as can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not faile us, if we faile not with the condition: The conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that indeed is propoſed hypothetically, and doubtfully. <hi>If ye have been planted into his Death.</hi> But ſo is not the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe: that is direct and Categoricall, without any <hi>If</hi> in t. <hi>Ye ſhall be alſo into the likeneſſe of his Reſurrection.</hi> Shall be without doubt, if you continue unmoveable in your Winter
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:168881:10"/>plantation, and pluck not your ſelves from the Tree of Chriſt Croſſe; That Cro-ſſe is a Tree of life, that will not ſuffer you to die or wither; but ſhoot you forth again, into a better plantation.</p>
            <p>Howbeit, Take heed of preſuming, for though we cannot periſh, while we continue faſt joyned to the root, we may break our ſelves from the root, and ſo periſh. <hi>If a man abide not in me, he is caſt forth as a witherd branch,</hi> Iohn 15.6. <hi>Behold the goodneſſe and ſeverity of God, On them that fell, ſeverity, But toward thee, goodneſſe: if thou continue in hi goodneſſe, otherwiſe thou alſo ſhalt be cutt off, Rom</hi> 11.22.</p>
            <p>So that in our unſtedfaſtneſſe there may be danger, but in his promiſe is no unſtedfaſtneſſe. If we continue not, yet he abideth faithfull; he cannot deny himſelf: more than one or two places of Scripture like this, aſſure us, that we cannot miſſe of a glorious and high plantation; if we abide firm in a lowly one and be conſtant in true Repentence, then it is a faithfull ſaying. <hi>For if we be dead with him, we ſhall alſo live with him: if we ſuffer, we ſhall reign with him,</hi> 2 Tim. 2. <hi>Knowing that as we have been partakers of the ſuffrings, we ſhall be alſo of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation,</hi> 2 Cor. 1.7. <hi>For ye are dead, and your life is bid with Chriſt, in God. When Chriſt who is our life ſhall appeart, then ſhall ye alſo appeare with him in glory,</hi> Col. 3.4. <hi>He that raiſed up the Lord Jeſus, ſhall alſo quicken our mortall bodies.</hi> Ro. 8.11. Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the like Teſtimonies aſſure us, that our diying in Chriſt, is but the Gate of riſing to life, we cannot be loſt in the firſt plantation, if we wait with patience for the ſecond. And as true, that the two plantations are inſeparable (as was ſaid) no arriving to a glorious ſummer, but through a hard winter, no happy riſing with Chriſt, unleſſe we die with him. And if any riſe not by a new and holy life, after their repentance and conformity to his ſuffrings, it is a ſign, they were never well <hi>planted into the ſimilitude of Christs Death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So then the connexion of the two plantings is undeniable: they may not be ſevered. But as touching this latter planta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion into Chriſts riſing, wherein (ye will aske) conſiſts that? Or what is it, to be ſo planted. Interpreters are here divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded:
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:168881:11"/>ſome; becauſe the chapter throughout, is an exhortation to good life, and the words before are; <hi>Baried with him in Baptiſme into death:</hi> That like as Chriſt was raiſed by the glory of the Father, ſo we to walk in newneſſe of life: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive by this planting into the reſurrection of Chriſt, is meant onely our ſanctification, as by the other planting into his Death is meant our true Repentance and Mortification. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers again, becauſe the two parts appeare in the nature of a Promiſe and Reward, conceive this latter plantation to point at our eternall reward, and the likeneſſe of Chriſts Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, to be that ſtate of immortality, wherein Chriſt now abides, and which at the end of the world, all his true mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers ſhall partake of: both expoſitions are profitable, both uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and both have great abettors: for the former of ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, are <hi>Ambroſe, Jerom Bede</hi> and <hi>Cajetane,</hi> for the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of glorification, are <hi>Chryſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtome, Theophylact, Euthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mius</hi> and <hi>Athanaſius;</hi> we ſhall (God willing) touch upon both, as the time will permit, and ſo conclude, with a word of Application.</p>
            <p>And firſt, we ſhall be planted into the likeneſſe of his Reſurrection, that is by our ſanctification; In nature this ought to go firſt, for it went firſt in Chriſt; even before his Body was glorified, while he was in his mortality, his ſoule was perfectly holy, and enjoyed the viſion of God. Theſe two eſtates of Chriſt: <hi>viz.</hi> Before his reſurrection, and after, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent our two Reſurrections. One of the ſoule to Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and Holineſſe, begun in this ſtate of mortality, another of the Body, glorified with immortality, at Chriſts ſecond coming to judgment. The ſoules reſurrection leads the way, called therefore in Scripture; the firſt Reſurrection. <hi>Bleſſed and holy is he, that hath his part in that: For over ſuch the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Death ſhall have no power,</hi> Revel. 20.6. Two deaths we read of, before the end of the world. The ſouls death in ſin, and the bodies death in the Grave, Both would have their reſurrection. But firſt the ſoule from the Death of ſin, to the life of righteouſneſſe; which is by Grace: And then the Body, from corruption to Immortality, which is by Glory.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:168881:11"/>
            <p>To begin with the ſouls Reſurrection to the life of Grace; obſervable it is, that this alſo is a plantation ſupernatural as well as the life of Glory. No praiſe to us then in any good fruit we bear, but to the Root Chriſt Jeſus, the Root of <hi>Jeſſe,</hi> whereinto we are planted, <hi>Without me,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>ye can do nothing;</hi> for it is God that worketh in us, both to will, and to do according to his good pleaſure. What haſt thou, which thou haſt not received? Even the power and will of beſtowing and doing good to others, is none of ours to boaſt of, it is beſtowed from on high. Ye ſee here, the Apoſtle promiſeth ſuch a Reſurrection by way of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. Ye ſhall be planted, ſo as to bring forth good works: Not as if you were able to bring them forth of your ſelves, but God will plant you, ſo that ye ſhall be able to bring them.</p>
            <p>The reaſon why the Apoſtle uſeth this Metaphor of plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, may be to ſhew how entirely we are beholding to Chriſt, and to his Reſurrection for the whole power of well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing; As alſo to let us know, that our fruit bearing in Chriſt, is the very end of our planting. Therefore we are planted indeed for the fruits ſake: for when that cometh then it appears we are living plants, then is our Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection juſtified; as good we were dead ſtill, as barren and yield no encreaſe to our Maſter. If no fruit, then no part ſure in this plantation, nor in the firſt Reſurrection.</p>
            <p>Well, but by what means is this planting brought to paſs? (ye will ask) or, how are we grafted into Chriſt's Riſing? By Faith (ſay ſome): for Faith is that by which we live the life of Grace, called therefore ſometimes <hi>the life of Faith.</hi> Faith unites us, that's certain, for by it <hi>we dwell in Chriſt, and Chriſt in us, that Chriſt may dwell in your hearts by Faith,</hi> Epheſ. 3.17. Others ſay, by Hope. <hi>Bleſſed be God who haeth begotten us again to a lively hope, through the Reſurrection of Jſus Chriſt from the dead,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.3. Others again by Love; for Love is the moſt uniting Grace of all, which makes us one with Chriſt, and Chriſt with us: one undivided, and not to be ſeparated: for, <hi>What ſhall ſeparate us from the love of Chriſt,</hi> Rom. 8.35. Indeed by all three we are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporated
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:168881:12"/>into Chriſts myſtical Body, and therefore en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liven'd and planted in our firſt Reſurrection.</p>
            <p>But eſpecially, and above all, is this Reſurrection to appear by a holy Converſation, in newneſs of life: This is the live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Image and ſimilitude of Chriſt's Reſurrection; that, as he was changed from mortality to Glory, ſo we from our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer corrupt converſation, to holineſs and righteouſneſs. We are grafted into a better ſtock, that we ſhould hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth bring forth better fruit; in vain are we new grafted, if our fruit be ſtill the ſame. As the grave made a great change in Chriſt, his glorious Body far differing from his frail and paſſible one: ſo, our lives renewed by Repentance, muſt be far eſtranged from former ſinfull courſes, All is to be new framed after the Image of the new Man; old things are paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed away, behold I make all things new: for if any be in Chriſt, he is a new Creature. A new heart, that which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore delighted in vanity, now in perfection of Vertue and Purity. New hands, thoſe that were wont to hurt and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraud our brethren, now exerciſed in helping and relieving them. New tongues, thoſe that were given to lying and diſſembling, to railing and curſed ſpeaking, now filled with bleſſing and truth, inſtruments of Gods Praiſes. New eyes, they that ſo much joyed to behold beauty and vanity; now flowing with water for their youthfull follies. New feet, thoſe that were ſwift to ſhed blood, now ſhod with the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration of the Goſpel of Peace, and prepated to run the way of Gods Commandements. The whole man new, not after the Image of the old Adam, in the deceivableneſſe of unrighteouſneſſe, but after the Image of the ſecond Adam, in ſincerity and Truth. This is rightly planted into the Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude of Chriſt's Reſurrection, by being new framed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his glorious Image.</p>
            <p>And ſtill we may go nearer. For the likeneſs of Chriſt raiſed again, is the very Image and likeneſs of God, ſaith <hi>Leo.</hi> Now Gods likeneſs is in all Heavenly Vertue; far above all paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and frail perturbations is his eternal Conſtancy. He is all Mercy, all Truth, all Goodneſs: imitate him what we may; be mercifull as your heavenly Father is mercifull, kind
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:168881:12"/>as he to the unthankfull and evil: who ſends his Rain upon the juſt and unjuſt: long-ſuffering, full of patience, and ſlow to take vengeance. Moreover, ſee that all be in a right ſtate of Government, for Chriſts glorious Body is wholly ſubject to the will of the Spirit; let our bodies alſo be in a right ſubjection to our ſouls, and our ſouls in ſubjection to the Law of God. Let our ſenſe be ordered by our reaſon, our reaſon by the Precepts of holy Scripture, and eſpecially in the manner of your vertuous working, endeavour to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble your Pattern, for there is the right trial indeed. Herein lyeth the main difference betwixt men regenerate and unregenerate: betwixt thoſe conformed to Chriſt's likeneſs, and thoſe unconformed. That from a true Chriſtian his works come eaſily, voluntarily, delightfully, like the motions of Chriſt's glorified Body; but from the unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate they proceed heavily, cheerleſly, weariſomly, Ian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guidly, and interruptedly. Will ye then diſcern the truth of your Plantation into the Riſing of Chriſt? Obſerve the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of your fruit-bearing, whether what ye do vertuouſly, ye do delightfully, heartily, chearfully, conſtantly, abundantly, without any tediouſneſs or wearineſs of well-doing? If ſo, then ye <hi>may gather ſome</hi> comfortable aſſurance, that ye have your part in the firſt Reſurrection; in which if you hold out with patience, will without fail bring you to the ſecond, for that followeth as a Reward upon this, and it is a Reward worthy waiting for indeed: <hi>If ye have thus been planted into Chriſt's Reſurrection</hi> myſtically, ye ſhall be really; If ye had thus reſembled him in ſoul, ye ſhall in body alſo; and that brings us upon the laſt point of our diviſion, and moſt proper to our comfort over the dead, to wit, the Reſurrection of immortality and glory, and our planting into that: <hi>Ye ſhall be planted into the likeneſſe of Christ's glorious Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this may well be called a ſummer Plantation; for in the bodies riſing, mans nature ſomewhat reſembles that of plants. Plants after they are wither'd in the depth of Winter, begin to ſpring again at the opening of the year, and returning of the Sun. The Sun of Righteouſneſs Chriſt Jeſus, when
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:168881:13"/>he returnes, ſhall make a ſpring ſeaſon, wherein all the bo dies of dead men ſhall riſe, here they have their fall of the leaf, in affliction and ſickneſſe, the dead winter in the Grave; but they ſhall inſallibly have their ſpring againe: <hi>Thy dead men ſhall live</hi> (ſaith Iſaiah) <hi>Their dead bodies ſhall ariſe, thy dew is as the dew of hearbs, and the earth ſhall caſt forth her dead.</hi> Iſa. 26.19. Of plants none doubt it, they die and ſpring againe, there is hope of a tree, if it be cut down, that from the root ſomewhat may ſpring; But <hi>man lieth down and riſeth not,</hi> Job. 14.12. Nay man ſhall riſe alſo, the nature of man ſhall now reſemble the nature of plants, by this new and divine plantation, they ſhall have a new ſpring, and a better ſummer, at the return of a better ſun, and be more vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous than ever.</p>
            <p>For it is planted into his reſurrection, and his reſurrection is glorious, and glorious for ever. Chriſt being raiſed from the dead, now dieth not: Death hath no more Dominion over him, which makes the difference betwixt Chriſt's mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and others that ſhall riſe; That Death may have do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion over them, but not over Chriſts members, that riſe after his likeneſſe; for they ſhall riſe in glory. <hi>When Christ, who is our life ſhall appeare, then we alſo with him in glory.</hi> And we ſhall be like him, for we ſhall ſee him, as he is Like him? and ſomewhat more. More than reſemblence is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, even a kind of union; <hi>I in them, and thou in me, that we may be made perfect in one,</hi> John 17.23.</p>
            <p>This therefore is the plantation, moſt properly intended by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> for he ſpeaks in the future, ye ſhall be planted, and <hi>ſhall be,</hi> intimates hope, and hope would be of ſome glorious reward; ſomewhat worth our waiting for. But the Reſurrection of Grace to holineſſe and Righteouſneſſe, ſeems rather a labor than a reward, becauſe of the imperfection, and troubles that attend it in this life, the fears, the cares and temptations. Shall be planted then, points to ſome bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter eſtate, than this life can hope for, even to that of 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.58. <hi>Wherefore my brethren, be ye ſtedfaſt, unmoveable, always abounding in the work of the lord: for a much as ye know</hi> (upon his hope to wit of the bodies riſing againe) <hi>that now your abor is not in vain in the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:168881:13"/>
            <p>But take this hope away, and our labor is vaine indeed, then they that are fallen aſleep in Chriſt, are periſhed. There muſt be a Reſurrection therefore (ſaith <hi>Cryſoſtome</hi> on this place) or God ſhall not be a full rewarder of them that ſeek him; They that ſeek him moſt, ſhall labor in vaine, for how poorly is vertue recompenſed here? yea, the beſt ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, Conſtancie, and Striving for the truth unto death are leaſt of all rewarded. If no other life to be hoped for, Chriſtians were doubtleſſe, of all men moſt miſerable.</p>
            <p>But now is Chriſt riſen (ſaith the Apoſtle) and riſen, as the firſt-fruits of them that ſleep, and therefore they that belong to him, muſt riſe like him. This fleſh now ſubject to wormes and duſt, ſhall be clad with a new garment of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality: he that made it of duſt, is not ſo weake, that he cannot raiſe it out of duſt again, elſe if no Reſurrection (ſaith <hi>Damaſcene</hi>) let us even turn Epicures, eat and drink, and live a beaſtly life, and ſo an end: If no reſurrection, what differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, not onely betwixt holy and profane, but betwixt men and beaſts, nay, if no Reſurection, happier were the beaſts that know no care, feele no cumberance, are not diſquieted with ſorrow for what is paſt, or feare of what is to come! If no Reſurrection, then neither God nor Providence. All things are hurried by chance and confuſion, how many good men in this life have we ſeen heavily opreſſed? And on the ſide of their oppreſſors, there was power: but they had no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter; how many wicked ones, may we ſee unjuſtly proſpering? no bands in their death; but they are luſty and ſtrong: they come in no misfortune like other folk, nor are they plagued like other men, their eyes ſwell with fatneſſe, they cotrupt others, and ſpeak wicked blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies. How can this be endured, if God be righteous, and wiſe and all power in his hands? <hi>Erit ergo, Erit Reſurrectio,</hi> (ſaith that Father) There muſt, there ſhall be a Reſurrection, for God is not untighteous, to forget their work and labor of love which have ſuffered for his ſake. If the ſoul only have ſuffered in vertuous works. It perils and conflicts have fallen upon the ſoule onely, let the ſoule alone be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded; But if the body, the fraile body hath undergone
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:168881:14"/>toyles and paines: if ſhe ſweat and faint, hunger and pine, and be even martyr'd and mangled for Gods ſervice, let either the body ſhare in ſome proportionable rewards, or confeſs God a weak, if not an unrighteous Maſter.</p>
            <p>Of the bodies Reſurrection therefore no doubt to be made, ſuch a plantation it ſhall have: but wherein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth the ſimilitude (ye will ask) to the Reſurrection of Chriſt? School-writers anſwer in two things eſpecially: that is to ſay, Clory, and Impaſſibility; the one defending the body from all harm, the other crowning it with all good. Two wayes (we know), a Glaſs that is broken may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived reparable, one to be made whole as it was before, but ſtill brittle, ſubject to caſualties and apt to crack again: another ſo repaired, as to be changed into a ſolid hardneſs, or metall-like firmneſs, not to be broken any more. The former of theſe is like the Reſurrection of <hi>Lazarus,</hi> or of <hi>Jairus</hi> his daughter: the later like unto Chriſt's, where this frail Glaſs of mortality ſhall be changed into firmneſs and immutability, no more lyable to breaking: this mortal to put on immortality, and this corruptible to be cloathed with incorruption. And again, over and above ſuch im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſibility ye may ſuppoſe added to the Glaſs Charity, and reſplendency to give light of it ſelf, like a Carbuncle or Glow-w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n, or the Moon in a clear night. This likewiſe ſhall be added to the bodies impaſſibility: namely, Light and Glory, <hi>The Righteous ſhall ſhine as the Sun in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of their Father,</hi> Matth. 13.43. Such is the likeneſs of Chriſt's Reſurrection.</p>
            <p>In fine, the Schoolmen here tell us, of the ſouls and the bodies Dowries, when the Heavenly marriage betwixt Chriſt and his Church ſhall be conſummate, and they are ſeven, three in the ſoul, and four in the body: three in the ſoul, to anſwer to the three divine Vertues which ſanctifie the ſoul in this life: namely, Faith, and Hope, and Charity. Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Faith ſhall anſwer clear and beatifical Viſion, whereby we ſhall ſee God face to face. Unto Hope fruition, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we ſhall enjoy that we ſee, and apprehend that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we are apprehended. Unto Charity union, implying
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:168881:14"/>fulneſſe of joy and delight, in the preſence and poſſeſſion of him whom our ſoul loveth: Thus ſhall the ſpirits of juſt men in theſe three be made perfect.</p>
            <p>In the Body ſhall be four more Perfections or Dowries, curing all defects and penalties incident to this mortall fleſh, which are ſpecially four, <hi>viz.</hi> Heavineſſe, Groſſeneſſe, Paſſibility and Ignominy. Heavineſſe, diſabling it to move upwards, or to make any great ſpeed in paſſing any way. This ſhall be done away by agility, whereby the body ſhall become light and ſpeedy as the wind, able to be whereever the ſoul would wiſh it in a trice. Secondly, Groſſeneſs, not ſuffering it to enter in at a narrow place, or to paſſe, as water doth, through a chink; but by reaſon of its ſtiffe and groſſe conſiſtence, it is barr'd out with doors and locks. This ſhall be remedied by the gift of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tility, whereby the ſubſtance of the body, when ever the ſoul pleaſeth, ſhall become plyable as Oyl, or Water to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in at any cranny or chink, and yet not looſe its Figure, but return as it liſts to its ſhape and conſiſtence again. Thirdly, Paſſibility or frailty, expoſing our bodies to be harmed and injured by heat or cold, hunger or thirſt, fire or water, ſword or ſpear. This ſhall be removed by the gift of impaſſibility; our fleſh ſhall no more be lyable to hoſtile injuries: Violence ſhall not hurt it, Time ſhall not waſte it, Hunger ſhall not pine it; all diſeaſes, aches, pains and infirmities ſhall be far away: This is more than incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, for the bodies of the wicked ſhall have a kind of incorruption; they ſhall not die nor waſte away, yet they ſhall not be impaſſible, for they ſhall be tormented with Hell-fire: But the bodies of the Righteous ſhall be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſible, never to know pain or ſorrow more: all teares ſhall be wiped from their-eyes. Fourthly, Ignominy, our bodies are now ſubject to ſhame and noyſomneſſe, there is a Turpitude in the nakedneſſe of the body; 'tis lyable to evil ſmells, and un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>omely deformity: this ſhall be done away by the gift of Charity or Reſplendency: whereby theſe bodies ſhall be all bright, comely and lovely, filled with fragrancy and glory C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>leſtial, more beautifull in their
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:168881:15"/>very nakedneſſe, than any Apparel can render them. So, then in theſe four the body ſhall have all the perfections our hearts can deſire: even the excellencies of ſtrength, health, activity and beauty. The perfection of ſtrength it ſhall have in ſubtility; it can penetrate or paſſe through any thing. The perfection of health in impaſſibility, it can be harmed by nothing. The perfection of activeneſs in agility, it can be where the ſoul deſires in a moment. The perfection of beauty in Charity, or Reſplendency, far exceeding all mortal comelineſs whatſoever.</p>
            <p>Now, that we may not ſeem to go quite without book, as if no ground of all this to be had in Scripture. Obſerve, that we are to be planted into his Reſurrection, who ſhall change our vile bodies according to the likeneſs of his own glorious Body; and Chriſts glorious Body after his Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection had all theſe Agilities: for he appeared to <hi>Mary Mag dalene</hi> ſuddenly, and as ſuddenly vaniſhed. It was with the Diſciples at <hi>Emmaus,</hi> at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> with the eleven: with her at the Sepulchre, and all in a ſhort diſtance of time. Secondly, Subtility it had, for it paſſed through doors faſt locked, through the Sepulchre barr'd and ſealed, and was not reſtrained any where. Thirdly, Impaſſibility, for as Chriſt now raiſed, dyeth not, ſo death hath no more dominion over him: no ſickneſſe, infirmity or injury is his glorious body any more ſubject to. Fourthly, Charity, or Reſplendency: for it was not leſs glorious be ſure, than it was in Mount <hi>Tabor</hi> (a ſhadow of the Reſurrection) and there his face ſhone, and his Rayment became white as the Light; only it was in his power, now ſo to ſhine when he would, and when he would to ceaſe, and in that reſpect the more glorious ſuch a body. If then we are to be planted into the likeneſſe of his Reſurrection: if, as we have born the Image of the earthy Adam, we ſhall alſo bear the Image of the Heavenly. This is his Image, this his like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and into this if we have been rightly planted into the likeneſſe of his Death, we ſhall grow up by the power of his Reſurrection, which God of his mercy grant unto us all, even for the ſame our bleſſed Saviours ſake. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:168881:15"/>
            <p>Turn we now to a word of Application, upon this preſent ſubject of mortality here before us, and ſo I ſhall commit you to God.</p>
            <p>I am not ignorant, how hard it is to ſatisfie the expectation of ſo judicious and full an Auditory, touching ſo full a ſubject, and worthy ſo great commendations as the life of this Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Gentleman whom we are now to ſpeak of. Nor am I troubled at the prejudice of ſome, to whom he was leſſe known, and whoſe opinions are not much to be valued: I muſt not fear to bear witneſſe to the Truth, having for theſe eleven yeares paſt ſo well known him, and for ſome yeares lived ſo near him, and ſo throughly acquainted with him for his judgement in matters of Religion, as I believe toward his latter time, no man in <hi>England</hi> more: nor may I mince the matter, becauſe he was my ſpecial friend, one to whom for many real favours and neighborly cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſies, I was much obliged. I care not whoſe thoughts may charge me of flattery, or ſelf-ſeeking, ſo long as my own Conſcience chargeth me not for delivering any untruth, or ſmothering ought worthy commendable remembrance, for fear of detracting tougues.</p>
            <p>But I yield them too much reſpect in ſo long Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gizing. I ſhall for brevitie ſake paſſe over many things in his younger time worthy mention, becauſe I was no eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witneſſe of them. As that his natural parts were ſo emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent by Gods great bleſſing, as to out-ſtrip many of his rank at School when he was a child; and, being quickly removed from School to the Univerſity, from the Univerſity to the Innes of Court, that he there grew ſo eminent as to be called to the Bar betimes with much honour, daily increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in repute and renown, till be performed his publique reading with great applauſe; nor could he have miſſed the degree of a Serjeant, had times been as favourable as his worth was great. That though one of the youngeſt ſonnes of his Father, and by a ſecond Wife, yet ſo highly he gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed hi, Fathers good opinion by his conſtant dutifulneſſes and his known ability and worth, that long after the death of his Mother, his Father at his deceaſe ordained him ſole
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:168881:16"/>Executor, left him all his perſonal Eſtate beſides his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of land, ſuitable to the reſt of his children. Which over-plus bequeathed to him alone, he yet with ſuch charity and tenderneſſe imparted to his brothers again, that of his meer voluntary goodneſs, he gave them (as I am informed) to the value of 2000.</p>
            <p>Theſe things, received on hear-ſay, I let goe: and obſerve that in his honeſt induſtrie, God ſo bleſt him, that he grew to a fortune, ſuch, as ſcant any of his family had the like, yet not to be charged (for ought I could ever hear) of ruining any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or family, or riſing by the fall &amp; impoveriſhing of others. But eminent for his faithfull diligence, and honeſt truſtineſſe, and wiſe ſecrecie, and abundant ſufficiencie in his profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; ſo that great and eminent ones in the ſame profeſſion, and ſome elder than he have repaired to him for his opinion, and to be aſſiſted with his advice.</p>
            <p>In all the long time of his life and practiſe, never heard I of any that could taxe him of the leaſt breach of truſt, of any extortion, bribery, or injuſtice, or of being feed on both ſides, or for deſerting any cauſe, which he thought juſt, for want of his poore clients purſes ability. Well might he ſay with <hi>Samuel,</hi> whoſe oxe or whoſe aſſe have I taken, or of whoſe hand have I received any bribe to blind mine eyes withall? Notable late inſtances might be given of this, if particulars of this nature were fit here to be mentioned.</p>
            <p>His integrity ſo great, and his abilities ſo eminent, could not fail to have preferred him to a ſeat of judicature among the higheſt had not the tempeſt of the warres coverd him with a cloud. Wherein yet he perferred his conſcience before all worldly ends: nor followed any ſide, becauſe he thought it would proſper, nor forſook that ſide, when he ſaw it proſpered not, but perſevered as he had firſt ingaged, and engaged not weakly, but fervently, actively and couragiouſly. And yet ſo prudently, that though he ſuffered impriſonment, and payed large compoſitions, yet he ſcaped eaſier than ſome that were leſſe active. So great was his wiſdome, and in ſuch eſteem was his worth had, even, by the adverſe party: I will not ſay, he was courted by ſome of them, to accept of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:168881:16"/>among them, but ſuch things have been averred in my hearing, and to my knowledge his conſtancie was ſuch, the world could not have wrought him to accept of promotion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his conſcience, for all that was offered to our Saviour up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Mountaine.</p>
            <p>During the time of warres and troubles, though he were far in years, yet he made no haſt to marry. No, nor in times more quiet, before the war, though he could not have wanted great offers, as any man of his quality, yet he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred the diſcharge of his calling, and the continuall employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments he had that way, in the ſervice of many noble friends, before all conjugall delights, and no leſſe free was he from in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperance in eating or drinking. Where is the man can ſay he ever ſaw him cup-ſhotten, the reigning diſeaſe of this Town and Countrey as abſtemious was he knowen that way, as from pleaſures more effeminate.</p>
            <p>And when maturity of years and a faire eſtate of his owne, at length invited him to marry, in times more calme: he looked not farr abroad, to raiſe his fortunes, but choſe him a conſort neer home, of a neighbouring family, both worthy and eminent, one of his own perſwaſion, and whoſe Father had ſometimes been high Sherife of this County. With whom God bleſt him to live moſt happily and lovingly, and to have hopefull budds of poſterity, even in his old age. The greater ſorrow at preſent to all his friends, the babes ſhould be left fatherleſſe ſo young.</p>
            <p>And whereas he might have planted himſelf in the City neer his practiſe, or in Towns of more trade, and credit, than this mean place, ſo abounding with poore; he choſe rather here to fix his manſion, here to build and ſettle: and here to keep hoſpitality amongſt his poor neighbours, and to have the bleſſing and prayers of many ſuch, as how highly he deſerved them how conſtant a reliever of the needy, both at his dores, and in their houſes: how ready to lend to any in want, how bountifull at his Table, what a conſtant inviter of his poor neighbours at ſolemne times of the yeare, I leave it to many of this place to report, who
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:168881:17"/>have felt the benefit of it, and may condole the loſſe of it, as well as I.</p>
            <p>A great lover of antient good order he was, and no friend to innovations: a conſtant frequenter of the Church in quieter times, till his health began to fail him, and newer cuſtomes to creep in, which he fancied not. A devout Receiver of the bleſſed Sacraments, and a frequent Communicant in publick, when he might receive it in the beauty of holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, as he deſired to ſee it. Seldome failed he at the three ſolemn times of the year, eſpecially to make one at the Communion, if he were in the Countrey. To the ſuffering party of the Clergy, to thoſe of his own per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion very loving, kind, reſpectfull and bountifull. To none of any ſort, that I know, uncivil, though in more ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial manner, he favour'd &amp; countenanced Divines of known learning, gravity and experience, nor much reſpecting others, whom he thought time-ſerving, hypocritical, igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, raw or ſcandalous. A friend to Peace he was, though his profeſſion rather thrived by ſtrife: a willing Reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler and taker up of differences, where both parties would hear reaſon, rather than a prolonger of ſuits. A man, ſuch as <hi>Moſes</hi> would have choſen for a Judge, fearing God and hating covetouſneſs: hating it not only in himſelf, but in others: yea, not caring, to my knowledge, to diſpleaſe ſome of his very good friends, where he thought them too worldly enclined; very bountifull to the poor he was him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and would fain have had all of ability like him. Far from flattering, lying, and ſoothing up, though ſuch vices are too frequent with many of his profeſſion, loving Truth, and delighting in them that loved it, as one rightly ſenſible of the great calamities this Kingdome hath been involved in, through the licencious and unconſcionable liberty of lying tongues.</p>
            <p>Theſe vertues made him honoured and reſpected far and near; ſcant a Nobleman or Gentleman in theſe parts that made not much uſe of him, and frequently, as their occaſions required reſorted to him: ſo, that he was the emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:168881:17"/>beauty, ornament and ſhelter of this poor place where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he lived. A Staffe to the poor, a Counſellour to the rich, a Sanctuary to the oppreſſed, a Terrour to the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſcionable, deceitfull and worldly minded, a comfort to thoſe in need, and to ſuch as for need deſired his help.</p>
            <p>Our hearts ſorrow it was, that ſo ſoon in his bodily health he began to decline, having yet ſcant added three years to threeſcore: but to his joy in the end it proved, I doubt not, that he was ſo long a planting into the Death of Chriſt. The Croſſe of mortification from the time of his full maturity, might ſeem to be his daily practice, whereby he learned to die to the fleſh. The Croſſe of Tribulation he had his ſhare in too, having taſted of perſecution, as far as impriſonment and loſs of goods for his Conſcience, whereby he was taught to die to the world. The Croſſe of natural Death was his laſt tryal, whereby he learned to dye to mortality it ſelf, and to all the temptations of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan; and long he was a planting on this manner into the ſimilitude of Chriſt's death. Near upon two years I have perceived him declining: when as his outward man pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed, ſo his inward ſeemed to renew day by day.</p>
            <p>During which time, the Vertues before-mentioned as peculiar to the Croſſe of Chriſt, might ſeem more and more to encreaſe in him. To ſay nothing of his Piety, addicting himſelf to read Books of Religion, as his time would permit. And of his juſtice ſo true and upright in his dealing, ſo exact in paying every one his own. The four Vertues of the Croſſe ye heard commended: to wit, Humility, Charity, Patience and Conſtancy, appeared more and more to manifeſt themſelves in him, the nearer he drew to his end.</p>
            <p>Humility; for he was courteous to the meaneſt, ready to put off and yield reverence to any, as faſt as any to him: nay, to prevent in Courteſie, and to give place to ſome his inferiours. Charity, for he excelled in bounty to the poor: witneſſe his laſt charitable Gift to this Pariſh, and divers pious Legacies in his Will to the value, well nigh of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:168881:18"/>a thouſand pound, witneſſe his loving invitation of his poor Neighbours in his weakneſſe at Chriſtmaſs laſt, even when himſelf could not eat, yet it joyed him to walk by and ſee others eat and drink at his coſt. And for an emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent proof of his Charity but a little before he took his bed in his laſt ſickneſſe, he lent freely to one that had dealt falſely enough with him, and was like for ſo doing to be utterly ruined by the fraud of another: he lent, I ſay, to him notwithſtanding a conſiderable ſumme of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to preſerve him from periſhing. So notable was his Charity in returning good for evil, and ſo well he ſeemed to remember, <hi>If thine enemy hunger feed him, if he thirſt give him drink,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>It pleaſed God to enlarge his patience by the manner of his laſt ſickneſs, which ſeizing at length on his lungs, deprived him of the uſe of his ſpeech, for any length or continuance of ſpeaking: during which time I never ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in him the leaſt impatient carriage in word or deed, or any repining at the heavy hand of God upon him, but ſilently he ſubmitted himſelf under the ſcourge, like him that ſaid, <hi>I became dumb, and opened not my mouth, for it was thy doing,</hi> Pſalm 39. 10.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, For his Conſtancy, as he approved it in the courſe of his life, ſo to the death conſtant he was to the Religion he had been born and bred up in: an obedient Son of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as he had ever profeſſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be, and ſuffered for. Heartily he anſwered to all queſtions that were asked him about the profeſſion of his faith; willingly and readily ſubmitted himſelf to Gods will for leaving the world; gladly forgave all that had of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended him, and wherein he had offended any, profeſſed himſelf willing to ask forgiveneſſe, and to make reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution.</p>
            <p>Being put in mind of the Sacrament, he would not for reverence ſake receive it in the evening, but deferr'd it till the next morning, and then moſt piouſly and devoutly, like one that bowed the knees of his heart, when thoſe of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:168881:18"/>his body failed him, with eyes lifted up, and hands bent to Heaven, he received it: and when he heard after both kinds taken; Lord grant it may nouriſh you to eternal life, chearfully and audibly, he ſaid <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After which, he diſmiſſed us from longer praying by him, being deſirous to be left for the preſent to his own private devotions, and requeſted us to pray by him again in the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternoon, as if he had foreſeen the certain time of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture: and in the afternoon, according to his own ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment, at prayer we continued by him till toward five in the evening: at which time, moſt meekly and ſilently, and like a Lamb he departed, and quietly ſlept in the Lord. And now being ſo rightly <hi>planted into the Death of Christ,</hi> having thus ſowed in teares, we doubt not he ſhall be <hi>plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into the likeneſſe of his Reſurrection,</hi> one day in body, as he is already in ſoul, and reap in abundance of joy; which God of his mercy grant unto us all for Jeſus Chriſt his ſake. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
